with meaning let's just say it's oh I
think it is I think that that that
connectedness with what is that affords
transformation is what people are even
talking about in the psychological
literature ultimately about meaning yeah
so two things come up then to tie back
to previous things like that the
discussion of the origin I think
resonates with the discussion we were
having about tradition and then yeah and
then I think I think of the
Enlightenment right and the
Enlightenment rejection of tradition as
an oppressive it's a gnostic attitude
right it's in the pejorative sense of
gnostic the rejection of tradition as an
oppressive structure right that is
keeping us you know from the promised
future or something like that and then I
think that is bound up with what we were
also discussing this truncation of
rationality down to basically monologic
inferential argumentation and losing the
connection with Rati oh and logos those
two things seem to be coming to meet
together at sort of a historical moment
in the Enlightenment
mmm-hmm and that's pertinent to me
because we have people obviously the
question comes to mind is steven pinker
yeah basically saying enlightenment now
right there the problem is the doubling
down right the the the idea the problem
is we were just we just not accepting
how really really wonderful the
Enlightenment is and again to be high to
garyun about this is to not deny and
seriously to not deny everything the
Enlightenment has given us right and I
you know science isn't is an important
thing I'm a scientist I value it you
know the increase in in health care that
is not a minor thing in human existence
etc so not and so and he puts up all of
his graphs and there's no there's no
denying that well actually some of the
graphs I think are controversial but we
there's no denying most of the graphs
but that's but there's a sense of what's
the graphs for all the ways in which
they're graphic they missed the point
they missed the point of what the
like how the enlightenment again cut us
off from Rotti Oh and cut us off from
tradition and in that significant deep
way cut us off from a cultural cognitive
grammar for falling in love with being
yes yeah it's yeah it's yeah to make a
Haida garyun point of full agreement the
trouble is and enlightenment forgets
darkness concealment and yes in the
horror right yes yes that part of the
sacred is the horror yeah if you're not
open to horror you're closed off to all
and if you're closed off to aw
you wonder differs from curiosity in
that wonder calls everything into
question yeah but but yes and and on top
of that you could say horror comes back
to haunt you yes different level and
more from the middle and then you're no
longer even capable of dealing with it
because you're not used to it being
there being part at the heart of
existence you could say what why is
death so so extremely outsourced or the
not in in our epoch it's nobody spoke
about the the loneliness of the dying
this is a tremendous societal problem
but death itself what is it for the
Greeks for the Greeks death is at the
heart is an irresolvable mystery or
problem at the heart of off of existence
but for us today it's according to
Harare just a technical problem waiting
to be solved right and and I think maybe
pink it would be in agreement with her
are we here I don't know but when I that
interview you might know John Gray and
in is a British philosopher and in one
of his books I think the soul of the
marionette which is a reference to Han
Lee from Kleist he says that what he
sees with this new Enlightenment
movement by people like Richard Dawkins
in pink and others is that what's the
world they want to live in do they wants
to live as in the machine stops in a in
a bunker somewhere looking at grass
where they get
you a news feed every day how much
better the world is in terms of oh look
it's all going moving upwards with
what's hidden in these graphs is that
even if we've got all the best health
care and people live longer etc the
intricacies the prop the the existential
problems of being a human beings don't
go away they don't just disappear
they're still right you still have to
die you still face all the horror
everyone else has faced and and
hopefully not as bad as some some have
had to go through but still this is not
it forgets darkness this enlightenment
movement but it it brings back another
kind of darkness right if you keep
staring at the Sun the Sun will turn
dark he will turn blind you can't just
be in sheer light all the time yes yes I
agree with that I think that was very
very well said yeah it strikes me even
if we move to the sort of popular
culture because I talked about this in
talked about how even in my class how in
fact even many of the movies we call
horror movies are not horror movies
they're just you know they're just
I call them startled and puncture movies
they're just movies that are designed to
give us more and more intense
experiences of our fear of predation
we're wired to be afraid of predators
because we you know our you know all of
the previously we would preyed on for
very long time so that deep in us so we
can push that button just like you can
push you know the glucose button and
people will gorge on sugar and they will
gorge on the fear of predation but
there's very few movies that actually
give you like there should be something
that's on the same scale let's just be
an aspect of wonder in horror like in
wonder you call yourself and your grip
on reality right into question and
Horesh be like where you and your sense
of self and your sense of your grip on
things it's called radically into
question now there are some I found a
few there are a couple of movies that do
do that they try to do horror but I
think it bespeaks the point we're
talking about that popular culture
actually also and this is such a high to
get anything a
it hides horror under the mask of what
it calls were it actually prevents us
from encountering or yeah right but this
mask on front of it which makes it
basically a monster to be killed like
like all you have to do is actually if
you could just face your favorite
predation and turn and face the monster
yeah the doctor da right kind of thing
what it has no right horror should
should leave you with a mystery that
undermines your sense of you know
ultimate security that's part of what
horror should do for you a joke it
should be like it should have asked in
my to my mind it should have aspects I
think it is just psychologically it's
not a continuum with awe and Wonder yes
so yeah there's something you said about
about like bringing in a contemporary
culture right it's like where is it and
this is one of the things I'm I think
I'm getting more of a sense of okay to
relate with to look for the place that
where we can genuinely find the horror
right is the senses with which what's
really interesting is that and this is
one of the things about the this notion
of like detect the age of Technology
right is is that for example when I go
to actually I was in Atlanta visiting my
mom she lives in Atlanta and we went to
this some this temple that they had
actually shipped over block-by-block
from India and was a it was a like a
it's like a Hindu temple like to the
however I went in there and the whole
thing and every single part of it was
carved and animated and told the story
and I didn't even know what the story
was I couldn't understand it but like
you just it communicated just this deep
sense of this ever and fractal in sense
of yeah
recognized
of being nothing everything like you get
to the you get to the Senator thing you
look up and there's this like it goes
into it's like you're you're walking out
you just like present man like vibrating
it and then we walk back out and I
looked up and I looked across the street
and there's this like there's this
shopping center thank and there's the
people walking along and like this awful
this whole Road right with and I just I
was so struck and horrified but here's
the thing that's like here's the thing
that seems horrifying it's it's not it's
not that we live in places like that and
that they exist it's that and that
they're horrifying the horror is that
everybody's walking around and nobody is
saying this is horrible right so there's
very few people that are walking around
you're just in the flow of it but
they're as you look like at these houses
that are the same it's just a little bit
of difference like buildings are built
to look like something right versus
being something right yeah yeah there's
a that's where I feel a particular if
the thing the thing that is horrifying
and fascinating and I'm wondering if
this is like an example of starting to
actually look at the withdrawal right
seeing the withdrawal and being in
relationship to it is it seems like part
of the withdrawal is no one is noticing
the withdrawal right isn't that what
well yeah Nietzsche says in the
genealogy of morality and to all these P
also speaks at the whole robach we so
the shihoro of emptiness and he says
rather than not willing the will wants
nothing all right so I just I'd rather
become a great destroyer yeah yeah Fromm
said that too right wait and when people
can't make anything they'd rather than
doing nothing they'd rather smash
everything down because at least at
least they've got the last
messages of their agency yeah
so I wondering what about what I just
said
there's a sense in which people and I
mean that was part of the whole book
that I wrote with Chris and Philip like
a zombie
the zombie is is the is the being that
is completely unaware of the fact that
it's a zombie that it disconnected from
the world from itself from its Jeff
the zombie is all of the disconnections
unaware of the disconnections and it's a
symbol but you know Leo and Anderson I
we've reviewed a couple of movies on the
week that are going to come out on the
minding media with Joker in which you
see a shift from the zombie to something
were like and it goes to the point we
just spoke about where now of course the
Joker who spoilers here by the way
spoilers Joker is about the meaning
crisis I think that's very clear because
you know all of the tropes of meaning
you know his connection to his past is
undermined if the very story that we're
watching we lose any sense of dramatic
irony because we don't know what's real
and not in it right
his name is oxymoronic he's Arthur the
great king Fleck I mean is immediately a
meaningless piece of crap
Arthur flack like you know come getting
pounded over the head and then we see
him sort of devolve into all he wants is
whatever kind of attention is left right
that's all right there's no meaning no
value no connectedness it's just it's
just the sheer it's even beyond like is
even beyond sort of destructiveness it's
just right the you know the last
narcissism is the last vestige of
attention that well at least you know
things are people are still paying
attention to me and then what was
interesting about that is you know the
way the way again what we're talking
about instead of the shuffling zombies
at the shopping mall
you have the angry crowd in riot focused
on a figure that's not a leader in any
sense but who what who what what he's
doing is he's trying to make the
environment as absurd as
narcissism because that's the last bit
of conformity that's possible for him
that's the last bit of him having a
connection to reality available to him
right and so you I think and the fact
that that movie was so like popular and
got so much attention yes I people
aren't talking about it and so you're
right guy there's still zombies but I'm
afraid that we're actually moving to
something beyond them not talking about
it I think we're moving to the
possibility that they might start acting
out from it not acting on it but you
know how we talk about somebody acting
out like when they're acting out like
when a child is acting out an issue that
it doesn't properly understand right
that that's why I'm trying to use that
phrase because that's what Joker is
right he's that he's the child man
that's acting out how the meaning crisis
is shifting from the zombie horde to
like the north the the the violent
absurdist narcissist I think that's
something you really really pay
attention to and for me that that
brought with it again a kind of horror
that goes beyond so I'm not trying to
trump you or anything guy on the horror
of the zombie the horror of the zombie
is that bacon see right but the horror
of Joker is it it's a different thing
it's that this is now twisting in a way
that I think is extremely dangerous
extremely dangerous if if if it portends
if it is I think if the movie isn't just
a movie it is a myth of some kind it's
emerging the fact that it takes place
around a mythic character is also you
know kind of kind of something
thought-provoking I would say this is I
just want to make sure I got what you're
saying like that the extra that the new
loop around right which is it's not just
a vacancy right being a zombie it's that
I act out of being that that vacancy and
my only the thing you said about
conformities the last conformity
I am left to last way in which I can be
identical to the unfolding of being is
if being is private if the unfolding of
being is primarily absurdity right and
especially if that's how I'm
participating in it because a
narcissists existence is one of enacted
embodied absurdity like if then I've I
can if I can you know if I can make the
absurdity out there as comprehensive as
possible than it then at least I have
that final last ditch connect connection
to dance but this is extremely important
to think this through further and and
and it also make as many people as
possible aware because I think what
we're pushing against is is is you can
call it late modern subjectivity
hyper-modern subjectivity exactly
subjectivity collapsing into itself and
it's this it's it's becoming paranoid
you can see how it's losing its grip on
reality how it's losing its sense of
certainty that it was given by Descartes
and others right absolute sense of
certainty is now collapsing and all I'm
left with is as you said is this
absurdity is being unfolding as absurd
and now all I can do to make sense of
anything or posit myself again is by
acts of sheer and utter brutal violence
for example bring my horror that I can't
cope with because the world isn't
supposed to be horrible but somehow it's
completely absurd I bring this horror
into the world and I assert myself
within and give myself some certainty
before I ultimately collapse what I see
in all of the madness is subjectivity
pushing to its utmost limited I think
that was beautifully said I think that I
think that I think that developed my
point very well I really like what you
just said I think that's I think that's
an that dimension you added is
insightful it's interesting it's kind of
like there is this there was a sense of
that movie actually right as everyone
gathered along
did it look very much like some of the
some of the the protests at Berkeley
right like I remember walking out one
time I used to live right across the
street from Berkeley like the main
campus and I we had a meeting and
helicopters were going and you're
hearing noises and there's riots and and
it was just I don't know it was like Ben
Shapiro or something speaking right and
I walk outside and there was literally a
hammer and sickle spray-painted on all
the buildings and it was this um it's
interesting because I'm thinking about
this sense of like it was like it was a
very moral stance like how could you
have this whatever whatever the
assertion was about that person but it
was like uncanny it was eerie walking
out in in the streets afterwards and yet
it was very tied to a morality weirdly
enough and I'm and I'm just I'm just
when we at the end of that movie when
everyone was like right like total
immorality there's I do anything yeah
and I mean and the thing is I mean I
don't want to get into the politics of
this yeah yeah there it but but there is
there is the collapsing of morality to
the assertion of rules and propositions
so morality in those kinds of protests
has been divested from virtue its
disconnected from virtue in in some
really really important ways that needs
to be talked about again I don't I I
don't want to claim that people within a
democracy shouldn't protest obviously
good etc I'm not I'm clearly not saying
that but what I'm talking about the
content in which the protest is
expressed not the fact or the goal of
the protest okay so let's be clear about
that fact or the goal of protest when
talking about the content in which it
expressed and whether or not that
expression actually sits well with the
fact and the goals of protest I mean it
claims to be
it makes moral claims but
when you when you separate morality I
think from virtue especially the virtue
the virtues of wisdom and courage right
and software son then that your
protestations literally about justice
are going to be very hollow in an
important sense that we're talking about
you know and then so I see that as
actually what you get sort of before you
get what you see in Joker which is
you're pointing to you get the Prout the
protest that is just protest yeah
absolutely it's not even it's not even
it's even giving up the pretense of
virtue signaling or or making moral
assertions it's just smashing and anger
and let's just let's make everything
let's just let's just break apart
whatever structures are left because
structure itself intelligibility itself
has now become oppressive to us yeah I
agree with that
I agree and I think that's that's right
hmm now you see where we are we're in
the heck we're in the depths of the
meeting crisis when the dam is talking
about the meaning crisis yeah do you
think as a question on that that
intelligibility has become oppressive to
us is that has that anything to do with
what I would think of his paranoia of
late modern subjectivity I I think so
III think that we've lost and they're
like well you could correct me on this
but I think this is something I sort of
see in Heidegger I see it also in bit
consign in a way that intelligibility is
supposed to be something that gets us
beyond our subjectivity that it's that
it is not just about what you get what
starts to emerge right in the 11th
century it's not just internal coherence
amongst my my propositions right it's
not just the coherence yeah you know
that intelligibility is supposed to do
give me AK it's supposed to get it's
supposed to give me some kind of access
beyond my subjectivity and I think when
you you lose that right when you when
you lose that sense of intelligibility
that way then of course
ah isn't it going to go from being like
a lens through which you see if you'll
allow me this metaphor it it has it had
some bad connotations that I don't want
but if it goes I want to pick up on the
double sense of the word through right
then intelligibility is something I see
through like you know and and by means
up if I if I lose the sense of seeing
through all I'm gonna get is seeing
looking at and then that's a wall yeah
right that's a wall right if I can't see
through in both senses of the word
through that I'm looking at that's a
wall and that all it is is just the
echoing of my own subjectivity it's just
the prison right it's just the prison I
think I think that is exactly what
you're pointing to with what you said
and I that that's how I that's why I
placed so much like they talk a lot
about the transparency opacity shifting
of attention and we have to remember
that and then we have to somehow work
that back into our understanding of
understanding yeah yeah standing yeah
yeah because what I think is that just
in line with what you just said is so we
look at someone like 50 all right for 50
50 says something along the lines of I
always recognize myself in nature he has
to say that because nature is just
fiction for him yeah you have Hegel and
Schelling who tried to rescue nature a
bit but that had didn't really work out
and what I'm trying to say said what the
projectory were on is it the self
certainty of the self asserting self
referential subject or ego has lost its
certainty with the death of God
it was importantly and because God let's
not forget God it's a hypothesis that
Laplace no longer needs right god is a
hypothesis that descartes needs in order
to guarantee that the world out there is
actually there it's patience and make
sure they're actually all these people
out there they're not robots / psalm
bees where they're actually human beings
Scott makes sure of that but I can't
really be sure of that myself
is all I know is meaning me and once
this certainty disappears once the cows
are Suey this ungodly this non God like
God just evaporates into a never
exploding non cosmos and black
coal's what we're left with is something
subjectivity doesn't know and can't make
sense off so hence it it's as you said
stuck in a wall fucking itself and it
reacts violently and I keep sitting it's
because I don't want to pin it down on
anyone right because I think it is
ultimately structural historical yeah
but but there is to me at least it
clearly are parts out of it and they
have to do with what we talked about now
is you could say you call it tradition
you could call it sources or origin or
wisdom sources of wisdom etc those would
be find that those would be different
paths out of it into a different way of
as you put an understanding of
understanding that takes us out of
ourselves and into this the non
propositional collecting world well said
well said beautifully said yes what did
he just say here I just wanted something
hit you there well I got from that I
think I agree with the idea that you
know Descartes represents this pivot
point in which the conformity to the
world is withdrawn until the specious
moment of self-conscious conformity with
itself sort of pure subjectivity and
what Descartes needs is he needs he
needs he needs right something that
gives him egress something that gives
him a way out of that and God is
supposed to do that and but this is the
god of certainty right this is not the
god of sacredness this is the god of
certainty and the problem is that God
ultimately it operates as johannes says
and then what we get is we get trapped
but within this subjectivity and I think
it's not even that it becomes opaque I
would wanted to add that we it's
collapsing
because if what you're trying to find is
the moment of certainty its vanish it's
like it's like almost like a singularity
you're vanishing and vanishing
vanishing towards it and so the wall is
closing in and closing so rather than
paranoia you'll haunt us I would suggest
it might be something more like
existential claustrophobia that were
[Music]
that's what I heard that's what I heard
him saying yeah something it's something
about like if I just sit if I sit with
alright so it's like there's a sense of
like claustrophobia I am like I'm being
closed in right and the a rages come out
like joke boobies like all of that so if
we bring in if we bring back in Nick
Nick atashi the guy is returning yeah
it's funny I just find myself going like
okay so what is so if that's how it's
happening this is what how things are
occurring for us right yeah yeah if we
look at it like I just thought about
this of like okay what would what would
he do right and there's a sense of where
I was like oh he would probably I just
had this sense of it would just go and
something you would about and I think
this is one of the things that I like
kind of in a certain sense being right
sighs to what's actually happening and
being still being immortal and realizing
on some level that we are you know until
like ontological abeer it being is that
one thing that we can never get clear on
right the Western Western late modern
subjectivity we're all 50 ins as I'm
gonna say you know we're forever saying
but I am I I am i ich bin ich ich bin
ich closing in but that I know right
even if everything's absurd I can still
assert myself by bringing your horror
and absurdity to a hyper modern hellhole
but the other response would be I am
mortal I am nothing you begin with
nothing
I am sheer withdrawal and all of a
sudden who Shh go away that's the
exercise
because if I am nothing it doesn't you
know it's not a self this line my
holistic self-denial and I know
self-annihilation I shouldn't be nothing
of the sort
no there isn't this core self perhaps
but there is a sense of nothingness but
in a different way that we think of it
in the West right and beginning from
this stance you open up again and this
wall that John was describing this wall
disappears is no I I would yeah I'm
gonna say something that I think it's
definitely convergent with that you
mishit Ali would say as you move towards
the center of the self you're not moving
to the foundational certainty what you
do is you suddenly uncover the mystery
of the no thickness from which the self
is always emerging but never in some
sort of fixed and stabilized way and if
you can get and that the end of like you
know and I think I think James was
getting towards us too when he made the
distinction between the me and the I
the words aren't totally right but
that's what he was trying to get at he
was trying to get out when you move
towards the center you don't move to the
fixed foundation you actually move into
the no thickness you move into that
aspect of mystery that is it is I don't
like this metaphor but it's at the
center right you and so nishitani would
point to the fact that if you follow it
far enough in you find that there's no
difference between moving in and moving
out that there you find a different kind
of conformity rather than the absurdity
absurdity there's a deep conformity to
between the no thickness and the no
thickness and then that affords right
that affords you moving back into an
agog a that's what I see him
basically articulating so that if you
can see the no thickness as that which
affords radical transfer aiming rather
than as the privation of graspable
securable actuality then you can get out
of you can get out of the the
claustrophobia
that's what I see him is saying it's
because the West can only if you'll
allow me to use these two words because
the West can only represent no thickness
as nothingness that it can't make that
move and so all it does is keep right it
gets to that point it gets to that point
yeah and then actuality we need
actuality to come back to that so what
do you mean by that you're honest no but
the self is the actual yes rather than
the potential or the possible sorry yeah
yeah
yes exactly I'm sensei I'm just sensing
into that kind of figure ground shift of
like oh yeah it's a fundamental figure
ground shift yes and it's not it's a
perspective a participatory thing it's
not an argumentative thing yeah yeah in
that equation because argumentation
always works within a stabilized
perspective and an existential mode and
we're talking about a fundamental
reversal the argumentation can come
after and perhaps age an explication and
elucidation but the process itself is
not an argumentative process right so
it's like really like I'm wondering
about just the sense of so when I kind
of just feel into it like one thing is
like I I sign my taneous League oh
there's some kind of risk
like if the walls Kerr coming in there's
like a risk I in some way actually have
to
I'd almost like let go of all of Western
metaphysics right like there's a there's
some kind of leap in there of love
rather than pushing away but actually
whatever the experience is I keep
getting the sense of keep watching it
not like I getting the sense of
meditation in that sense of the word of
some kind of vulnerability to be with
the horror and everything that we're
talking about I'm just sensing a certain
kind of like a response is a certain
kind of vulnerability there is I mean I
mean within my own practice you get to
this place where you step into sort of
because you can't grasp it you can only
be it you can you can feel I'll use
youngness as language because it's
perfectly appropriate actually for the
phenomenology you feel the perpetual
withdrawal the meditation right the
perpetual withdrawal you you suddenly
it's like the back falls out from behind
you that's why I like Jewish yes look
it's a meditation you're stepping back
and you're stepping back and you're
looking at and you're looking at and
then all of a sudden the what you're
stepping back into and you get the sense
of like that that's why I like that
noise that you get that sense of you
know of withdrawal which is not the
sense of a thing it's not even the sense
of a presence it's that I I have no
other word for it it's just the
phenomenological experience of the sense
of withdrawal and that can be initially
really really as you can imagine
horrifying to people it can be very
horrifying right yeah especially having
caught you know having had facilitated
experiences of that horror that sense of
like everything slipping away very thing
that you just it's almost like the last
bit of concern or care is glittering
that and then at some point it goes then
you're everywhere there's a sense of
like that was a that's been my
experiences with those places where I've
done a Delic or I've had an experience
where it's like
Oh like the ground starts to slip right
and then I can't grip onto anything in
that sense of and then there's a kind of
like a some kind of threshold of where
it feels like a death of some kind right
and in dissolving and then the this
recognition that the whole time
the thing I'm expanding into was present
the whole time right somehow like and I
just there was some way I was standing
in relationship to it or identified it
had it show itself as that which was
horrifying just that that kind of
process yeah I agree
that's it sounds very similar to what
I'm describing look honey that's putting
me I mean obviously there's
argumentation and religion and
nothingness but religion and
nothing--there's should not be read
separate from a deep kind of meditative
contemplative practice just like you
shouldn't read the tile thn if you're
not doing a Chi Chuan here you're just
deeply not getting it in in a really
important sense yeah that's interesting
because I'm interested in which people
have these kinds of experiences because
sometimes um the phenomenology is one of
like almost like like I said this whoosh
and then the other is it's it's it's oh
my gosh it's like it's all it's it's not
directional you know sometimes the
withdrawal feels that way but sometimes
it feels more like everything is almost
holographically everything is opening up
almost like sort of you know the tiniest
describes the one you know all the forms
are reflecting and interpenetrating each
other but the one is what allows for all
the opening up and interpenetration that
is not actually in any one of the forms
effect did that get that to that that
that has actually become more common for
me than just just the withdrawal
right right yeah that sounds very
familiar - yeah totally
so the point I'm get back to it the
point nishitani is making of course is
of course again you don't stop doing the
argumentation I'm gonna keep saying that
didn't you create religion and
nothingness but you also do these
perspectival participatory
transformations and then there is some
kind of allow me this metaphor this
there's a deal logos between them the
and and the response is in that dialogo
so it's not in the text it's not just in
the meditative practice but in the yeah
ocean shit exactly like I started I
started meditating I went to a good
posture to retreat
right and then I think a few months
after that is when I started reading
being in time mmm and it I remember that
it after reading being time and
meditating couple hours a day back and
forth that it changed my meditation
right yeah it was a kind of a sense in
which you know like the reverse was also
the case I expect the meditation
afforded you seeing things in being in
time that you wouldn't have otherwise
seen that's what it we've circled back
around again about trying to get to the
place of the philosopher rather than
just gather their propositions and
there's yeah
there's all these and this is a law this
was a lot for a long time in the
Neoplatonic tradition that around the
text was a whole ecology of practices
and the text or the discourse and the
practices were always in dialogue with
each other yeah and this is what had Oh
brought out so beautifully I think this
was one of had those great points yeah
not to make this too biographical about
anyone but Heidegger had circles of
students that he invited over for long
extended sessions of simply thinking and
sometimes they would collapse and
sometimes they they wouldn't sometimes
they were successful and
and yeah as you know he worked with my
dad boss in the 50s to the late 60s who
was a Swiss psychiatrist in what was now
published as the sole econ seminars and
there are still people practicing
designs analysis or existential therapy
that came out of that it's a highly we
work with psychiatrists for a decade or
more until he couldn't anymore longer
and that was his way of of you know and
he provoked them but because they were
totally within a Cartesian framework
they were very often out rich but what
he said then you can't begin with the
ego you have to begin here you have
mandalas I mean darkness in the world
and it's being with I was it cetera um
but he but he never shied away from that
he it was it was about bringing it into
practice it it wouldn't have been him to
do it it would would need someone else
to do it that was not his role and he
was aware of this because for him this
was ontic this was something that others
would have to do and but he provided the
until ontology for that right his
thinking and yes it needs practice and I
see with students - I bet that it
actually it you know they come to
university and they're quite
enthusiastic and after a couple of years
they sound like everybody else
and rather than still having because of
what I always do it first seminar
first-year students
ancient philosophy why are you here
that's my first question
sometimes again
it is this relevant for the exam and
some time but sometimes I get my mug
everything I say will be amazing and I
bring it I keep bringing it back
remember back the first lecture why did
you come here because usually people are
drawn to philosophy for a specific
reason they're looking for something um
what is it that they're looking for well
usually they're looking for meaning why
are they looking for meaning and why is
it that I mean first of all why is it
that perhaps academic philosophy doesn't
really do this or it doesn't acknowledge
it but but second of all what is it that
can be done should be done must be done
in terms of providing again a space for
these exercises practices etc yeah like
I think I mentioned this to you last
time yeah my discussion that I mean guy
also notices you know there are emerging
communities of practice that are trying
to create set ecologies of practices but
what I often find is that that's missing
from them is is philosophy ah so there's
a lot of the other stuff around a lot of
the things that we're talking about in
this practices and movement practices
and authentic discourse practices and
narrative practices and all of this and
don't get me wrong I think this is great
and I and I actively work on to support
and facilitate this but what I often
find missing is the philosophy and
what's it what's what's uh what's
interesting about that right he's like
I'm wondering about like but did you
correct me if I'm wrong but the the
religion without religion religion
that's not a religion that's my like I
don't get the sense for from its that
you're not looking to build a
non-religious church or something found
a religion I will keep saying that
there's I'm wondering about if
that bringing the thing that unites all
of these practices the theory the
philosophy awakening because to me this
is about like philosophies about
awakening the Wonder Ray and having that
sense of things and I find with teaching
people that there is a sense where you
have to awaken it like in a that's why I
called it a wakening from the meeting
crisis it's it's because people aren't
walking in with an awareness and in fact
the idea word philosophy they they will
proactively feel that that's like
assaulting or something to being her
head or something like that so one of
the things I found is it it's like and I
think I've gotten better as a teacher
over the years in that sense of feeling
the place where you can have them see it
yes you can see that moment where like
they see something they experienced
something that was right in front of
them their whole lives yeah and it never
there's all it never been questioned and
it's a question and you can see that
awakening pouria that's really what
that's what really what Socratic aporia
is supposed to do yeah yeah YouTube what
you thought you what was so familiar and
so obvious suddenly is now mysterious
team in a profound way I mean that's the
whole point of Socratic aporia I agree i
I mean that's that's why you're honest
picked up on it that's why I try to make
a distinction between philosophy which i
think is still important by the way but
and philosophy a-- which i think is is
something more that i'm not i'm not a
i'm neutral on whether or not everybody
needs to do philosophy but i think
everybody needs to practice and live
philosophy a-- in a profound way and so
I think those are yeah because I guess I
want I want to pick up on that that
point you were making about you know you
you can bring Pete
to that point where they get well it's
to use our metaphor you get you get a
crack in the wall yeah opening right
it's like the Leonard Cohen lied well
you know there's a there's a there's a
there's a crack and everything and
that's how the light shines through all
right um
really yeah I think everybody because of
what we're in and where we are I think
that's why everybody ultimately needs
philosophy a-- so well I deeply applaud
and I really and I put time and effort
and talent into these emerging
communities I think there is still right
we've got to get philosophy ax into them
in some way that's why this discussion
is very important by the way that's one
of the reasons I mean other than really
liking you guys and enjoying the
conversation what I mean in this
conversation is precisely because I want
I think it's trying to do that it's
trying to bring philosophy ax into this
attempt to get these Ecology's of
practices going right on this point of
philosophy a perhaps also some other
point will have to carve out what that
is and what that means and you might
disagree with this totally both of you I
don't know but what are the dangers I
see in Hegel speaks of this I think in
the difference shift what he says it
would be absurd to call oneself a plate
in this today and and what I think what
he means by this is that you you can't
just pick and choose no no you can't
just go back and say well I'm an heiress
I'm a new in New York soon I'm an
Aristotelian I'm a played tennis and the
stoic I'm this and that as if from a
metaphysical supermarket because that's
very easy to do right I'm gonna be a bit
of a Buddhist over here I'm gonna but
what does it mean that that we have this
this rich source or origin but also this
miss this burden of all of this
knowledge because it philosophy is also
extremely abstract and and and well it
also is a burden to have access to all
of that potential knowledge and
the question is so if you use the word
philosophy a to some degree that's it
going back to the Greek word of course
that's the it won't feel but how for me
I think it would be extremely important
to to not be some isn't some part from
this isn't something uniquely off this
ebook right uniquely off this age that
speaks to this age but then that takes
of course direction and and and
reinvasion from the wisdom of what has
been but but doesn't sort of mix it up
too much do you see what I mean it sort
of it's it's generating itself out of
that which has been but in such a way
that responds to us but to us
specifically today in our yeah I totally
agree with that that's why I don't know
how to articulate it I've been tracking
I talked about salvaging which is my way
of trying to like you know you're sort
of diving into the depths and and
bringing up what was valuable and then
trying to refurbish it and it's a poor
matter for me I need a better one
yeah but that's part of what I'm trying
to say when I say the religion that's
not a religion
the reason why I think even for even
though I find Plato sacred and till
tiniest is sacred for me too I you know
I'm not a neoplatonist in the sense that
I can't the the actual age two worlds
mythos is not viable for me it's just
not viable of women so so well while I
want to respond to and I want to let the
I want to let the tradition flow into me
but exactly what you said yeah I want to
open to this I want exactly I think what
you're saying that's part of what I'm
trying to put my finger on with the
religion that's not a religion yes and
upon the sacredness but it yes for now
okay good not now I get oh I think I
understand that name better because it
reminded me of Heidegger's unnamed gods
yeah he doesn't name them because he
doesn't want to give us oh look you
should believe in Susan Hera
no we can't go back to Greek mythology
that would be a bit ridiculous so
they're unnamed for now because this
unfortunately or fortunately who knows
is a an epoch where gods have
disappeared where the godly is
disappearing withdrawing but what we can
still say that there is a flickering
some lingering some some gloom of them
so there some something that's still
there that's still an echo of the divine
but we can't name it we shouldn't name
it because if because what I don't like
about isms is that they are already
there already ossified but it's already
I mean this isn't and that's it so this
is what I this is no but if we because
OMA that's almost again subjective is
just asserting itself right I'm I'm this
ISM and therefore everything's fine and
I have to worry about it no then that's
not the age we live and we live in the
age of four nothing makes sense to some
degree but this is the tide is already
coming back there is that it's like they
have Nietzsche speaks of the healthy own
tone right of the tone of the hell's in
bird which already here's the so it the
halcyon bird breeds during to two weeks
off a couple of weeks when when the
ocean is still and and knows that
tempest will come again and it's it's
prepared for the horror terror that's
about to come but it's so it but it but
it doesn't sort of what I'm trying to
say is this this way of thinking
feelings of fear is a good name for it
because it's also quite open right but
if we if we stifle it with isms then we
it's almost like we what happened is you
can produce a consumer product
right exactly exactly I mean and and so
part of it I think is actually a
bi-directional
critique which the one we're giving
voice to now is to try to try to try to
resolve this through nostalgia and
that's yet that's a deep mistake I think
also trying to resolve this through a
utopia which has a completed picture
of the future is also a deep mistake I
think these things are not the proper
framing that we need for what I'm
calling philosophy oh well that's the
work and that needs to be done right
that's the whatnot sort of framing all
of Phaedo Sofia
but bringing while giving birth to Fela
Sofia yes it's more about exemplifying
and participating in it yeah again I'm
gonna I'm gonna be oh I will of course
theorize it because that's also yes
Robin my work step on it and then but
you know it's really interesting how
hard it is I mean I you know it's coming
sort of easy for us but it's hard to get
people because often if you say you know
give up nostalgia they go oh yes I get
that utopia or if you say to people no
no not utopia and they go oh yes I get
that nostalgia right and it's oh no no
no the the grammar that's generating
both of those is when I ask you to step
beyond and then that's when there's the
glimmer of horror in their eyes all
right yeah that's the moment that
requires deep respect of the person
you're talking to
deep sensitivity and a willingness to
linger and be patient with them and I
I'm sorry that came off as condescending
and I didn't mean it to be kind of
strange
I meant it to be caring yeah I'm gonna
have to go soon guys we've been talking
for two hours and I foresee that we
could talk for without any without any
difficulty this was extremely fruitful I
found this very helpful and also deeply
joyful to participate well thank you
very much with all over the both of you
well I'm hoping this this is the first
of many of these I would like it if I
could have the file of this because I'd
like to put them so I'm going to upload
the discussion
had with your harness to my voices with
verve a key a sight that comes up one
Sundays at 1:00 and I would be great if
I had this as a follow-up oh oh I got
sent it over to you
that'd be great you know let's let's
look let's keep doing this let's meet up
again and let's do this again because
III found it extremely valuable also we
just want to say that that from my
experience of doing these great and
putting them up and having people watch
them if these things in themselves is
awakening yes well totally meeting and
there's just granted like a hero fights
right rights participation it does yeah
something I just want to say that like
what the very thing that we're talking
about is actually like actually the
thing that the thing that we're doing in
some regard and just people watch yeah
yeah no as I've heard people talk about
like it awakened something in there yeah
totally that's the logos it's what we're
both what we're explicate and
exemplifying are in deep resonance with
each other and they're mutually
affording each other that's part of the
logos for sure for sure so we will talk
again soon I hope yes